"Previously on The Mentalist..."
Our fugitive is a known associate
of the serial killer Red John.
She's wanted for murder,
conspiracy, kidnapping
and weapons violation.
Lorelei has taken a hostage.
Need a ride?
Lorelei hasn't contacted me
in years.
I'm guessing you had a vain,
selfish, and controlling mother
and you found the strength
to pull away.
I sold Lorelei's sister.
I don't remember reading
anything about a sister.
Miranda.
That was her name.
Where is Miranda now?
She's... she was murdered.
She's dead.
Losing my sister brought me
into my full reality.
- Nothing can hurt me.
- It's nonsense, believe me.
Things can hurt you.
Jane, what's going on?
Have you been kidnapped?
Yes. I'm in fear of my life.
I can't talk long.
What happened to Miranda?
Before Miranda died she carved a message
into the warehouse floor.
- What'd it say?
- It says "Roy."
Your buddy Red John...
he killed your sister.
That's not true.
- You don't want it to be true.
- Just stop!
God, you're just like him.
I only wonder why the two of you
didn't become lifelong friends
the moment you shook hands.
I'm never gonna convince you
that Red John killed your sister.
You need to go and find out
the truth for yourself.
You know where to find me.
Hey.
Wake up.
Hello, Julia.
What do you want?
You know exactly
what I want.
You want me to stop?
Then tell me
what I wanna know.
I told you.
I don't know anything.
You don't know anything, huh?
I don't know.
I didn't know your sister...
- Sure about that?
- I don't... I don't know anything.
You sure you don't know?
Okay!
I'll talk, please. Just...
Stop!
I wasn't involved
with your sister's death.
This Lorelei Martins...she broke
into the home last night.
She assaulted the victim,
cuffed her hands and feet
and tortured her
for well over an hour.
- Does this have audio?
- Unfortunately, no.
We don't know
what they're discussing.
How did you get this on tape?
We found a nanny cam
hidden in the living room.
A neighbor said the victim had it
because she suspected
the housekeeper was stealing.
Well, we appreciate Sac P.D.
bringing us the case.
Hey, boss.
Victim's name is Julia Howard.
38, single, lives alone.
She manages a battered women's shelter
here in Sacramento.
Doesn't seem like the kind of person
Lorelei would target.
No, she doesn't.
Family, friends, co-workers...
they all say Julia was a saint.
Dedicated her life
to helping others.
So why did Lorelei kill her?
Any thoughts?
Jane?
No, no thoughts.
Okay, you and Rigsby need to look
into every aspect of Lorelei's life...
her mother, her sister Miranda
even Red John.
We need to find the connection
between Lorelei and our victim.
You got it.
- No thoughts?
- No.
This is Lisbon.
Yes, sir.
I'll be right there.
- It's Bertram. I gotta go.
- Okay.
You coming?
No. Sorry.
- Am I interrupting?
- Oh, no, no. Come on in.
Teresa, you remember Bob Kirkland
from Homeland Security?
- Of course.
- Agent Lisbon.
Bob and his team
were interested to hear
about the return
of Lorelei Martins.
Can imagine.
Her arrest continues
to be a priority for Homeland.
I've heard you say that in the past
but you've never said why.
Lorelei Martins is a known
associate of Red John.
She escaped from prison.
She kidnapped
your colleague Patrick Jane.
Which are all valid reasons
for the CBI to be involved
but Homeland?
You deal with terrorists.
We have a wide range
of investigative interests.
- I have to learn that trick.
- Which?
How you speak
without saying anything.
Well, I'll try to be more direct.
Director Bertram has been
kind enough to offer
CBI's resources
in finding Lorelei Martins.
Sir?
Well, you and Homeland
won't be working together directly
but Kirkland and his team
will have full access
to your investigation.
We'd like to be kept
in the loop.
Bertram is bringing Homeland in
on the Lorelei murder.
Did you hear me?
Yes.
Now that she's killed someone
they're gonna start looking again
into her escape.
That's likely.
Jane. I know you broke her out of prison
and you know I know.
- And I know you know I know.
- This is not funny.
If they find out you could be charged
as an accomplice to murder.
Well, if they find out.
They won't, unless, of course,
you sing to the coppers.
Which I won't, and that makes me
an accomplice to murder as well.
Well, only if you look at it
like a very persnickety lawyer.
She tortured someone.
Yeah. It's...it's horrible,
I-I know.
But she must have had
good reason.
- God, can you hear yourself?
- Yes, I hear myself.
Julia Howard must have helped
murder Lorelei's sister
must have been there
with Red John.
Lorelei wouldn't do this
otherwise. I trust her.
Jane... I am your partner,
not her.
You need to be honest
with me.
I know.
If she contacts you
if you find anything out
about her
if you have any insights
into the case...
I will tell you.
Now the tally needs to be
filled out once every morning
and once every evening.
- Okay. No problem.
- Thank you, Karen.
Hello. Can I help you?
I guess. I'm Agent Lisbon
with the CBI.
This is Patrick Jane.
Kevin Rome. I'm one of the trustees
here at the shelter.
Is there someplace
we could talk?
We wanted to ask you some questions
about Julia Howard.
Of course. The rest of the trustees
are right outside.
Jane. Are you coming?
Uh, no, I thought I'd just
take a look around
if... that's all right.
- Of course.
- Thank you.
Julia was a wonderful woman
so giving, so selfless.
I can't think of anyone
who had a negative thing
to say about her.
How long did Julia work
at the shelter?
Eight years, but...
I mean, she did
so much more than that.
She practically ran the place
single-handedly.
That's why we're all here...
to try and fill in as best we
can until we find a replacement.
None of you actually worked
at the shelter.
No, we serve an advisory role
and help with fund-raising.
But we volunteer
when we can.
Did you ever hear Julia
mention the name Lorelei Martins?
- No.
- No. Is she a suspect?
We're working
several different angles.
I saw on the web site
that there was a fourth trustee?
Steven Doppler.
He's flying up from L.A. tomorrow.
We're, uh, meeting with candidates
to fill Julia's position.
So soon?
The meeting was already scheduled.
It's our monthly meeting.
I know it seems cold,
replacing her so quickly
but the women at the shelter here
they...they've suffered enough.
Their safety and security...
that comes first.
Julia would have wanted that.
How can we get in touch
with Doppler?
He'll be with us all day tomorrow
at the Fairchild Hotel.
That's where we're meeting
to interview new candidates.
- Did Julia live in Sacramento?
- Jane, I'm in the middle of questioning.
Yeah, it won't take long.
Did she?
- Yes.
- And you're certain?
Yes.
She lived here for...
For as long as I've known her.
Eight years, at least.
- You sure?
- Pretty sure.
Lisbon, I'm gonna head on.
Your colleague...
he's, uh, very... odd.
Yes. Yeah.
Lorelei.
Did you miss me?
You murdered someone.
What'd you think I was gonna do
when you set me free, Patrick?
- You tortured them.
- I knew you'd be upset.
You're not as tough-minded
as you'd like to think you are.
So I wanted to see you.
I haven't gone off the rails,
I promise.
I know what I'm doing.
Julia Howard got exactly
what she deserved.
- She helped kill my sister.
- Helped who?
Not Red John.
She didn't know him.
But I know who to go to next.
Well, whoever that is,
they work with Red John.
Maybe. Maybe not.
- I'm gonna find out.
- Someone from the shelter?
I have to go, Patrick.
You're foolish doing this on your own.
Let me help you.
No.
I've done terrible things.
Unforgivable things.
There's no way back.
You and me are
on different roads, I hope.
Wish me luck.
Been doing some background
on Julia Howard
and I think
I found something.
She owned a home
here in Sacramento
bought it eight years ago
but she also leased a house in Davis
at 1309 Orchid Lane.
I don't understand.
Was she renting it for somebody else?
Unlikely. She doesn't have
any family in California.
Did she even have the money
for a second house?
Not on her salary.
Where's Jane?
- Haven't seen him.
- Well, thanks.
Okay.
Evening.
We had an agreement.
No more lies.
And I haven't.
You didn't tell me
you were coming here.
- Was Lorelei here?
- Yes.
Damn it, Jane.
Well, I didn't know she would be.
I was just following a lead.
Which you didn't tell me about.
You know, I tell you about 30%
of what I do.
That doesn't mean
that I'm lying.
Anyway, Lorelei confirmed
that I was right.
Julia was involved
in Miranda's death.
Oh, you'll have to forgive me
if I don't believe her.
Miranda must have stayed
at Julia's shelter.
I'll check it out.
- Where's Lorelei now?
- She's gone. She left.
What do you mean, she left?
Did you try and stop her?
Well, even if I could,
I wouldn't.
She's trying to figure out
if Red John killed her sister.
I need to let her do that.
And you think when Lorelei finds out
she's gonna tell you his name?
That's the hope.
You're putting your trust
in the mistress of a serial killer.
- She's playing you.
- Playing me? How?
You're blind.
You're involved with her.
- It's clouding your judgment.
- There's no involvement.
- I feel nothing for her.
- Now you're really lying.
I'm gonna make this
very simple.
I will not be a part
of this anymore
and neither will you, if you
wanna remain with the team.
An ultimatum?
Someone's playing
a little too much poker.
I confess.
I may have some feelings
but if I have crossed
any lines
it is not because
I like her.
I will do anything I can
to get to Red John
but you have known that
since the start.
Director Bertram.
I will be there
in the morning, sir.
- Does he want an update?
- Yes.
- And what are you gonna tell him?
- I don't know.
You do realize that if Bertram and Kirkland
get to Lorelei before us, then...
I'll never see her again.
She won't tell me
who Red John is.
I don't know what
to tell you, Jane.
"No, that's fine.
No, whatever you think."
No, no. I'm sorry.
That's fine.
Thank you.
No, thank you, ma'am.
All right.
Well, where are we?
Uh, we've made some progress.
Unfortunately,
there's nothing substantial.
Now I don't wanna bore you
with the details.
I see. What about Jane?
Does he have any insights?
You know Jane.
He's got theories.
I love a good theory.
If any of them were good,
I'd share 'em with you.
You know, Lisbon,
I've always respected you
which is why I'm going to be
completely forthcoming.
Please.
When it comes to Lorelei Martins
I don't think Jane can be trusted.
I don't know if that's true.
Well, he's admitted
to his sexual relationship with her.
Then Martins kidnaps him
and they spend days alone together.
And don't you ever wonder
what went on between them?
If there's something going on,
you... you can talk to me.
Thank you.
I'll keep that in mind.
If that's all...
Great.
What do you think?
You work with her.
You'd know better.
Clearly she knows more
than she's saying.
But... good detectives
always keep their cards close.
But can we trust her?
Can we trust anyone?
Morning, boss.
Whatever you're doing, stop.
We have a lead.
Julia Howard may have been involved
in Miranda Roman's death.
What do we have to go on?
It looks like Miranda
stayed at Julia's shelter.
Find out what was
going on there.
Sure, boss. Yeah.
What?
Thanks for not telling Bertram.
I don't wanna be thanked.
Too late.
Hey, boss. Just got back
from the women's shelter.
- What'd you find?
- Nothing.
This is their official intake log.
No evidence of Miranda Roman
ever staying there.
- Well, that's strange.
- Here's what's stranger.
The detective who
investigated Miranda's murder
is positive that Miranda
stayed at the shelter.
She had an abusive ex-boyfriend
and spent some time there
five years ago.
He said it would have been
a week before her death.
All right, talk to everybody
who was on staff
around that time and dig deeper
into their records.
- Figure out what we're missing.
- I'm on it.
Wait. Stop it.
- Get off your brother.
- He's gone rogue, mom.
Hey! Stop!
Come on!
She's got a gun!
Look! She has a gun!
Run!
Hey!
Hey, hey!
Stop or I'll shoot!
Get down on your knees!
Get rid of the gun!
- CBI?
- What happened?
We got report of a gunman
that matches the description
of your homicide suspect,
Lorelei Martins.
- Was anyone killed?
- No. Security guard was injured
but it looks like
he's gonna be okay.
Where is she now?
Not clear. She escaped on foot.
My men are searching the area.
But we did find something
in the suspect's vehicle...
a pair of handcuffs,
pliers, and a stun gun.
She's planning
to abduct someone.
"We were standing outside a hotel
when we heard someone screaming."
And that's when I saw her
standing there.
She had a gun.
She could have killed me.
We don't believe that was
her intention.
You don't believe?
That's reassuring.
Can you tell me
what she did want?
It appears she was planning
to abduct one of you.
Good lord. Why?
Why the trustees?
You think she thinks one of them
killed her sister?
Well, it looks that way.
Probably thinks they were helped
by Julia Howard.
She's kinda doing
our job for us in a way.
Shame we can't give her a call.
Yes, it is.
Any ideas which trustee?
Nope.
Did you know a woman
named Miranda Roman?
No. Why?
We believe she stayed
at the shelter.
I wouldn't know
about that.
I don't have anything to do
with the day-to-day operations.
Who did other than Julia?
I'm not exactly sure
what you're looking for.
Basically, anything we can use
to determine whether or not
someone stayed
at the shelter.
Well, you have the official
intake log, right?
Right.
Other than the daily tally,
that's all there is.
Wait. What daily tally?
I don't know. I told you...
I was involved in fund-raising...
parties, galas,
that sort of thing.
At the hotel, which of the trustees
did the gunman seem to target?
I couldn't tell you.
Pick someone.
First name that comes to mind.
I don't know.
Hey, we got something.
So I looked into the shelter,
and I found something strange.
This is the shelter's official record.
Miranda's name's missing.
- Oh, that much we already know.
- Right.
But the shelter also keeps
a daily tally for state records.
It doesn't list names,
but it keeps track
of the number of women
staying at the shelter.
Here's what's weird.
During Miranda's stay there's a
discrepancy between the two records.
In the tally, there's a woman
unaccounted for.
What does that mean?
Well, it means someone
was doctoring the books.
Yeah. Someone was trying to erase evidence
of Miranda Roman's stay.
Not someone. Julia Howard.
And there's more.
Yeah. This isn't the first time
it happened.
So far, I've found five instances
of women unaccounted for.
It's a pattern.
It's what it's all about.
Okay, here's what we're gonna do.
I'm gonna release the trustees
but I'll have an agent
sit on each of their homes.
"Rigsby, you take Jason Lennon.
Cho, you take Kevin Rome."
"I'll have Karl sit
on Stephen Doppler's hotel."
"I'll take Melissa Enfield."
"We'll be in radio contact
the entire time."
- If Lorelei tries to go after one of them...
- She will.
Then we'll be there to stop her.
You're not coming.
Yes, I am.
Jane, listen, I know
you wanna be a part of this
but I need you to stay...
Well, there's no reason
for me to stay here.
There is a reason.
If things go wrong,
you need to be far away.
You're in too deep.
Jane, I'm asking you,
please stay here.
Hey, Cho. You there?
Yeah. What's up?
What's going on?
Did you need something?
Yeah. Uh, well...
Hey, what do you think
Van Pelt's up to right now?
It's 5:00 a.m. She's sleeping.
You know what I mean.
Well, she's at a computer
training program.
She's probably using computers.
I should have signed up for that.
You barely know how to turn
a computer on.
What do you think
they teach you there? Duh.
Hey, Jane, what's up?
Rigsby, listen to me.
Lorelei is going after Lennon.
Are you sure?
Yes, I'm sure.
It's the fishing line.
- The what?
- "Well, I'll explain later."
Rigsby? Are you there?
You there? Rigsby?
"Rigsby."
Hey, Jane.
Lorelei is at
Jason Lennon's house.
I think Rigsby's hurt.
We need to hurry.
I'm on my way.
Cho, Karl, get to Rigsby's location now.
I'm calling for backup.
Please. Please. Don't hurt me.
I don't wanna hurt you.
I just wanna talk.
Rigsby? Rigsby?
You all right?
You're okay.
I don't know.
- Patrick.
- Thank God.
I told you, I need to do this
on my own.
No, you need my help now.
Police will be here very soon.
Do they know I'm here?
No, not yet, but they soon will.
What the hell is going on?
Lorelei thinks this is just
about her sister
but we both know better,
don't we?
What are you talking about?
You remember those other
five women from the shelter?
The ones Julia
helped you with?
Julia. Your partner.
She found the most vulnerable women
and she brought them
to you at her house.
This is crazy!
I'm a good person!
Okay.
So you didn't rape 'em?
No!
You didn't murder 'em?
You didn't bind their hands
and feet with fishing line?
No.
So I guess this isn't
familiar to you.
No.
Jason, look at me.
Look at me.
I'm the law.
I have to take you in.
I can't hurt you.
I can't kill you.
But she can.
And if you don't tell me
the truth right now
I'm gonna get up
and walk out of here
and leave you two alone.
No. Please.
All right, now you see
it's useless lying to me.
Tell me the truth.
I... work... for...
Red John.
Yeah.
He wanted Miranda
for some reason.
I don't know why.
He knew her boyfriend
was abusing her.
And she was vulnerable.
He told me...
to send Julia
to counsel her
to persuade her
to come to the shelter.
Julia brought Miranda to me
and I brought her to Red John.
And what did Red John
do to her?
- You know what he did.
- She needs to hear it.
Red John...
killed Miranda.
I'm sorry.
Thank you, Patrick.
Tell me.
Tell you what?
Red John's name.
Ask him.
I need a head start. Sorry.
- Wait. We had an agreement.
- He'll talk. He's weak.
We had an agreement.
Well, I'm breaking it.
I've done far worse.
You're just gonna go kill
Red John?
You don't think he knows
what you've been doing?
He's got weaknesses.
He can die.
And I'm going to kill him.
It was good knowing you.
Sorry.
- You all right?
- Not really.
- Is he okay?
- Yeah, he'll be fine.
An ambulance is on its way.
You stay with him.
Okay.
Jane. What happened?
Lorelei shot him.
He had a pulse,
but it's gone.
- Where is she?
- I don't know.
Jane, let me take over.
No, no, I got it. I got it.
He knows who Red John is.
Come on.
He had a pulse,
but I can't...
I can't find it anymore.
Rigsby's on the way
to the hospital.
Good. We need to find Lorelei.
Let's have C.H.P.
set up roadblocks.
- She can't be far from here.
- You got it.
What are you doing here?
This crime scene is now
under the jurisdiction
of Homeland Security.
Have your agents stand down.
- Get him outta there.
- Jane, stop.
You get away from me.
- Step away from me.
- No. Stop. Stop it!
- Get out of the ambulance.
- No!
- Jason Lennon is now my witness.
- Jane, let it go.
- No!
Jane!
Come on.
Any word on Lennon?
The doctors are keeping him
in a coma.
They can't risk
taking him out yet.
You can't get
the case back.
It's only been two weeks.
I'm trying.
Isn't why you're here, is it?
Okay. Let's go.
I'm sorry.
She had it coming.